

SOFTWARE + DATA

A Stockholm, Sweden | ■igor@fer.st | %igor.fer.st | Oigorferst | Inigorferst

Summary.

I'm an experienced engineer who loves helping data scientists and analysts extract insights from complex, large-scale data. I've spent 12 years supporting technical data needs across a variety of domains (insurance, healthcare, capital markets, and others) as both a data engineer and software engineer.

I have deep experience across the entire data stack: designing and building pipelines, ETL, data modeling, and executing analytics/data science projects. I focus on aligning technical work with business needs, and enjoy engaging directly with data users around requirement gathering and validation, training and upskilling, etc.

Work Experience

Bridgestone Mobility Solutions

Stockholm, Sweden

SR. DIRECTOR OF ENGINEERING/DATA ENGINEERING LEAD

Feb. 2021 - present

My startup Mobikit was acquired and its product incorporated into Bridgestone's software portfolio as a data-driven fleet risk management product for insurance carriers and fleet owners. I continue to lead data engineering and product development.

- Oversee the design and implementation of our telematics data pipeline, with a focus on scalability, reliability, and observability.
- · Manage globally distributed team of data and product engineers: hiring, onboarding, coaching, optimizing processes.
- Manage personnel and cloud budgets, set technical priorities.
- Own and execute high-value customer implementations.
- Technologies include: Python (Django/DRF/pandas), SQL (PostgreSQL), AWS serverless/RDS/EC2/Kinesis/Glue, Docker

Mobikit Columbus (OH), USA

CO-FOUNDER/CTOJan. 2019 - Feb. 2021

Technical co-founder of a startup building a data analytics platform for large-scale vehicle telematics data. I oversaw data

engineering, product development, and customer implementation.
Architected and led development of data pipeline to ingest, harmonize, and enrich telematics data from heterogenous sources.

- Defined and validated data model with current and prospective customers.
- Oversaw design and development of platform's analytics features and executed ad-hoc analytics and data science projects.
- Contributed code across the entire stack, from data pipeline to ETL to application backend to UI.
- Implemented data security and data governance features to meet enterprise requirements.
- Raised funding, guided company to product-market fit, and exited successfully.
- Grew and managed globally distributed team of developers.
- Technologies include: Python (Django/DRF/pandas), SQL (PostgreSQL), AWS serverless/RDS/EC2, Docker, Javascript(React)

Root Insurance Columbus (OH), USA

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER/DATA ENGINEER

Sept. 2018 - Jan. 2019

Worked at a growth-stage insuretech unicorn on various data-intensive projects.

- Prototyped a machine-learning model to enhance insurance rate accuracy.
- Implemented support for new rating methodologies and executed historical backtests for rating changes.
- Python SME for engineering and actuarial teams.
- Technologies include: Ruby (Rails), Python (scikit-learn), Ansible

Enlace Health Columbus (OH), USA

LEAD SOFTWARE ENGINEER Sept. 2014 - Feb. 2018

Enlace is a healthtech company building large-scale data analytics tools to support innovative models of healthcare delivery. I joined as an early employee working on the analytics platform, and was then asked to lead a team building a new product.

- Designed novel graph algorithm as part of PySpark ETL pipeline for health claims data.
- Led a cross-functional team building a care management and revenue cycle management product for surgical centers.
- Owned product design and technical architecture, maintained product roadmap, implemented features.
- Introduced and trained engineering team on new technologies (Docker, Angular), development processes (TDD, code reviews), and agile methodology (user stories, estimation).
- Technologies include: Python (Flask, PySpark), Javascript (Angular, Node.js), SQL (PostgreSQL, Redshift), Docker

June 21, 2023 IGOR FERST

InSample San Francisco (CA), USA

SOFTWARE ENGINEER Mar. 2014 - Sept. 2014

First employee at a healthcare analytics startup building a cloud-based tool for statistical de-biasing of clinical experiments.

- Designed and built the product protoype together with the CTO.
- Prepared fundraising materials and interviewed prospective customers.

Google Mountain View (CA), USA

SOFTWARE ENGINEER Feb. 2013 - Mar. 2014

Part of the conversion tracking team building tools that Google's customers use to understand the effectiveness of their ad spend.

- Implemented a novel conversion tracking visualization for the AdWords suite of analytics tools.
- · Developed enhancements to Google Analytics machine-learning algorithm for attribution modeling.

Palantir Technologies

Palo Alto (CA), USA

Jan. 2011 - Jan. 2013

FORWARD DEPLOYED ENGINEER

I worked on Palantir Metropolis, a data integration and quantitative research platform for capital markets.

- Product owner and developer for platform's visualization and reporting features.
- Embedded with the platform's largest customer, a prominent global macro hedge fund.
- Trained users in data analysis tools and gathered product requirements.

Skills_

General Data engineering, software engineering, product management, data science, technical leadership

Languages Python (primary), SQL, Javascript, Ruby, Java

Frameworks Django/DRF, Pandas, React, Rails

Infrastructure AWS (RDS, EC2, Cloudformation, serverless, Kinesis, and more), Docker, PostgreSQL, Github

Technical Expertise Statistics, optimization, machine learning, data modeling, graph algorithms

Education

Cornell University

Ithaca (NY), USA

M.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

- PhD candidate in Applied Mathematics supported by a US National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship.
- Published original research in algorithms and optimization: https://tinyurl.com/ycheu4us

University of Waterloo

Waterloo (Ontario), Canada

M.MATH. IN COMBINATORICS & OPTIMIZATION

University of Chicago

Chicago (IL), USA

B.S. IN MATHEMATICS WITH HONORS

Volunteering

Odesa Peace Fund Stockholm, Sweden

• General IT guidance and support for a US-based nonprofit providing humanitarian aid to Ukraine.

Hack OHI/O Columbus (OH), USA

• Twice served as judge and mentor for Ohio State University's student hackathon.

United Schools Network Columbus (OH), USA

- Designed and taught a three month after-school programming course for middle-school students.
- Developed spreadsheet-based operational tools for school administrators.

Columbus Arts Festival Columbus (OH), USA

- Member of organizing committee for 2016 and 2017 festivals.
- Built mobile-friendly web-based interactive festival map.

June 21, 2023 Igor Ferst 2